Something incredible in the world of
aviation and geography is happening next
year in 2027.
Throughout all of our lives, we've
generally believed that the world is
about as well connected through air
travel as it could already possibly be,
and that everywhere is just a short
flight away from anywhere else. And yet,
one of the world's largest airline
markets has never been directly
connected to two of the world's other
largest markets. To date, there's still
never been a regularly scheduled
non-stop commercial airline flight
between the heavily populated East Coast
of Australia and Europe or the US East
Coast, which means that residents of
major Australian cities like Sydney and
Melbourne, both home to more than 5
million people, have never been able to
take a direct flight to places like New
York City or London. The major reason
why is simply due to sheer geographic
distance. If you took Australia and
placed it on the exact opposite side of
the world, you'd see that it'd be placed
in the North Atlantic, right in between
Europe and North America. Thus, Europe
and the US East Coast are about as
geographically far away from the
Australian East Coast as you can
possibly get, since they're basically on
the opposite ends of the planet from
each other. And to date, our technology
has not been good enough to enable a
commercial airliner fully loaded with
passengers and cargo to make that entire
long journey that far non-stop.
Establishing a non-stop direct
commercial flight between Sydney and
London, two massive, culturally similar,
English-speaking cities on nearly
opposite ends of the Earth, has long
been considered to be one of the holy
grails of the aviation community for
nearly a century now, and one of the
final unbroken frontiers left on the
Earth for global aviation to surpass. As
long ago as 1989, commercial airliners
like the Boeing 747 have technically
managed to make the entire journey
between them non-stop, but they were
always test flights filled with special
fuel and were always virtually empty
without any passengers or cargo to save
on weight to extend their range. The
trick was always to find an aircraft
that can actually make the entire
journey with a full payload of
passengers and cargo on board, which
until today has remained elusive and
just out of reach technologically, but
not for much longer because next year in
2027, Qantas Airlines is finally
expected to introduce direct non-stop
service between the two cities for the
first time in history. It will be the
culmination of the past decade of
relentless technological advancement and
engineering by multiple companies. At
the end of nearly a century of air
travel between the two cities that has
always involved at least one stopover
point along the way. It is poised to
completely revolutionize travel between
the largest cities of the UK and
Australia and upon its opening, it will
immediately become the longest non-stop
flight in the world lasting for roughly
22 straight hours. That long of a flight
might sound like a nightmare to you, but
when you consider that it'll enable a
human being to travel from one side of
the world to the other in less than a
day and when you consider how brutal the
journey between the UK and Australia has
been historically, that 22 hour journey
that'll start next year will seem like
nothing other than a technological
miracle. In the long era before the
advent of air travel, the journey
between the UK and Australia was a slow
and grinding one. In the late 18th
century when Britain began colonizing
and settling Australia, sailing between
them took between 8 and 12 months each
way. By the time of the 1850s and 1870s
with the advent of fast clipper ships,
the journey time was dramatically
reduced down to between 70 and 120 days.
And with the later advent of steamships
and the opening of the Suez Canal
between the 1870s and the First World
War, the journey time was cut down even
further to between 30 and 50 days. It
wasn't until after the end of the First
World War that travel between the UK and
Australia could actually be accomplished
in less than a month And it came with
the first ever flight between them in
1919.
Known at the time as the Great Air Race,
six contestants took part and the
victors were a pair of Australian
brothers, Ross and Keith Smith, who were
accompanied by two mechanics. Together,
the four men flew a modified Vickers
Vimy bomber that had been developed
during the First World War across an
odyssey of the Eurasian continent
towards Australia that covered roughly
14,350
km. Starting in London, the team planned
for at least 14 stops along the way to
Australia for rest, refueling, and
maintenance. After departing London, the
plan called for stops in Lyon, Rome,
Cairo, Damascus, Basra, Karachi, Delhi,
Calcutta, Akyab or modern-day Sittwe in
Myanmar, Rangoon or modern-day Yangon,
Songkhla or modern-day Songkhla in
Thailand, Singapore, Batavia or
modern-day Jakarta, and Surabaya before
the final arrival at Darwin in Northern
Australia. However, along the way, the
team had to make nine additional
unscheduled stops due to unanticipated
weather, fuel, maintenance, and
operational needs that cropped up, which
brought the total number of stops they
had to make along the way to an insane
23. All in all, it still took this team
in 1919 a whopping 27 days and 20 hours
to fly between London and Darwin with a
total amount of flying time in the air
of 136 hours along the way. But in doing
so, the barrier had been broken. They
proved that flights between Britain and
Australia were possible and that for the
first time in history, travel between
the two land masses on opposite sides of
the planet was able to be accomplished
in less than a month's time. And it
would only keep on improving from there.
And the dream of eventually establishing
a continuous non-stop flight between the
two continents was born. 16 years later
in 1935, Australian based Qantas
Airlines and UK based Imperial Airways,
one of the predecessors to British
Airways, jointly opened the first ever
commercial air routes between the UK and
Australia running between London and
Brisbane. But it was still a brutal
ordeal when compared with air travel
between them today. Flights only
departed once per week and the total
travel time took 12 and a half days to
complete. When departing from London,
the flight would have to stop in Paris
where passengers would take overnight
train to bring DC where they would then
resume the flight portion with further
stops in Athens, an overnight stop in
Alexandria, another stop in Gaza, an
overnight stop in Baghdad, further stops
in Basra, Kuwait City, Bahrain, and
another overnight stop in Sharjah, more
stops in Wudayr and Karachi with another
overnight stop in Jodhpur, even more
stops in Delhi, Kanpur, Allahabad, and
another overnight stop in Calcutta,
followed by yet more stops in Akyab,
Rangoon, and another overnight stop in
Bangkok, followed by a stop in Alor Star
and another overnight stop in Singapore
with more stops in Jakarta, Surabaya,
and an overnight stop in Rambang,
followed by a stop in Ko Pang and
another overnight stop in Darwin with
one final overnight stop in Longreach
before finally arriving in a Brisbane 12
and a half days later after having left
from London with no less than 28
scheduled stops along the way. Multiple
different aircraft were used for the
different sections of the route and only
around 10 passengers could be carried
along it as the flights departed once
per week. And for the privilege of
getting between the UK and Australia in
just 12 and a half days in 1935, the
price for a ticket on board cost 195
pounds, which in modern 2026 value is
more than 50,000 US dollars.
Nonetheless, the leap from the 1919 race
to the 1935 scheduled service between
the UK and Australia was a remarkable
achievement. The trip time was cut down
by more than half in just 16 years, and
it went from a daring expedition only
undertaken by pioneering aviators to
something that a wealthy passenger could
reasonably actually buy a ticket for.
And as the technology advanced further,
both the price and time would continue
climbing down more and more as well. By
1938, Imperial Airways opened up the
first-ever London to Sydney service
relied upon new Short Empire flying
boats, which were novel because they
didn't need paved runways or
infrastructure to land at. They just
needed rivers or harbors, which in the
1930s were much more abundant across
Eurasia than paved runways were. The
international terminal in Sydney back
then wasn't even really an airport at
all in the modern sense, but a flying
boat base in Rose Bay on Sydney Harbor,
where passengers boarded from docks and
slipways as if it were a maritime voyage
instead. The Short Empire flying boats
were able to cut the number of stops
between the UK and Australia in half,
down from 28 to only 14. While they also
cut the total travel time down from 12
and a half days to nine and a half days
instead. As you'd expect, the Second
World War significantly disrupted the
travel market between Australia and the
UK for all kinds of reasons. But by the
summer of 1943, Qantas managed to figure
out an insane workaround that is
important for the lore behind Qantas's
modern route today. In order to
reestablish the lost aerial connection
to the UK, Qantas cobbled together five
Consolidated PBY Catalina aircraft that
they were able to use to make the first
non-stop commercial flights across the
entire Indian Ocean. Beginning in Perth,
Western Australia, the Catalinas were
flown to their maximum intensity for
more than 3,500
nautical miles clear across the Indian
Ocean to an RAF base at Koggala on the
southern shore of Sri Lanka, which at
the time represented the longest
non-stop commercial air route ever
devised. Navigated entirely without the
aid of radio, the crews on board were
forced to rely entirely on just basic
navigation tools like a compass and the
stars. With departure strategically
timed so that the flight would cross
through Japanese occupied territory
under the cover of darkness, and with
the flight times lasting between 27 and
33 hours, the crew and passengers on
board would witness two sunrises along
the way. And it remains the longest
airtime for a commercial flight in
aviation history still to this day. Once
they arrived in Sri Lanka, passengers
would be transported by ground to
Karachi, where they would continue on
along their way to London.
This service became known as the double
sunrise service, and in a nod to their
own history of pushing aviation's
boundaries, it is what Qantas has named
their current direct Sydney to London
service after, Project Sunrise.
By 1944, Qantas began calling their
revived route between Sydney and London
the Kangaroo Route for the first time.
Named after all of the stops or hops
that their aircraft had to take along
the way between them, they were
reminiscent of a kangaroo's hops. After
the war ended, the flights clear across
the Indian Ocean were ended, and by
1947, Qantas took over the complete
operation of the entire route between
Australia and the UK for the first time.
Utilizing new Lockheed Constellation
aircraft, Qantas's restored and fully
operated postwar service between Sydney
and London could carry 29 passengers
between the two cities in as little as
four days, less than half the time it
took to do so pre-war. While the ticket
prices had also come down to the
equivalent of just 26,000 US dollars in
today's money, also about half of the
price that it was pre-war. And by this
point, the Constellation aircraft flying
the Kangaroo Route only required six
stops along the way in Darwin,
Singapore, Calcutta, Karachi, Cairo, and
Tripoli. With Singapore and Cairo
serving as the only remaining overnight
stops. Over the next decade, going into
the 1950s, several competitors to Qantas
opened up their own Sydney to London
routes as well. Qantas was flying four
flights a week. BOAC, one of the other
predecessors of British Airways, was
also flying four a week. While Air India
and KLM were each flying one a week. By
the end of the Super Constellation
piston-driven era in early 1959, Qantas
had managed to get the total travel time
along the route between Sydney and
London down to just about 2 days in 16
hours, utilizing about the same number
of stops as they had been in the
immediate post-war era. It was also
about the absolute limit that
piston-driven aircraft could reasonably
reach. But 1959 was an important year
for the Kangaroo route, because it's
also the year that Qantas first adopted
jet aircraft for the route. Qantas was
the first customer outside of the United
States to receive the Boeing 707
jetliner. And they immediately put them
on the Kangaroo route. And virtually
overnight, as the 707 jets replaced the
piston-driven Constellations, the total
travel time between Sydney and London
was slashed by roughly 40% or by about
25 hours through just a single
technological leap. The introduction of
the 707 enabled air travel between the
two cities to be accomplished in as
little as 38 hours. But it still
involved roughly the same number of
intermediate stops along the way as
during the previous piston-driven era.
The primary innovation of the 707 for
the Kangaroo route wasn't the reduction
in stops, but the sheer faster speed
that it could actually fly along the
map. Five or six stops along the way
between the cities was still required,
but for the first time, the entire
journey could be accomplished in only
about a day and a half.
>> [music]
>> In order to get rid of the number of
stops and save even more time along the
journey, jetliner technology would need
to advance further and range would need
to be improved. And both would
eventually come with Boeing's release of
the 747 in the early 1970s.
In 1971, Qantas introduced the 747 to
the Kangaroo route in another
technological leap forward. When
compared to the 707, the 747 could carry
more than double the number of
passengers and had a maximum range of
about 7,260
nautical miles compared to the 5,000
nautical miles of the 707. As a result,
the 747 could carry many times more
passengers along the Kangaroo route and
required significantly fewer stops along
the way. So, upon their introduction in
1971, Qantas' 747s could fly between
Sydney and London with only two stops
along the way in Singapore and Bahrain,
down from the six stops that were still
required with the older 707 jets. And as
a result, the travel time between Sydney
and London fell further by several
hours, while the price steadily came
down for passengers as well. For
Australia, the 747 was the aircraft that
finally transformed Europe from an
exclusive, elite destination into a
realistic holiday option for the middle
class. And as further improvements to
the 747's range were made by Boeing with
later editions, Qantas continued
improving the Australia-Europe
connection even more as well. In 1974,
Qantas was able to use the 747-200 model
to introduce the first ever one-stop
service between the Australian and
European continents. But it wasn't
between Sydney and London. It was
between Perth with a stopover at Bombay
instead. Because geographically, Perth
is about 1/6 closer to the UK than
Sydney is. The route between Sydney and
London using 747s still involved double
stopovers in Singapore and Bahrain all
the way until 1988,
when the new Boeing 747-300
finally enabled Qantas to introduce the
first ever one-stop service between the
two cities, eliminating the stopover in
Bahrain and retaining Singapore as the
only stopover along the Kangaroo route
still remaining. With this innovation,
Qantas managed to get the total travel
time between Sydney and London down to
only around 25 or 26 hours or just a
little over a full day. And this is
generally where the technology has
remained at ever since. In 1989, Qantas
did manage to set a headline-grabbing
record with a Boeing 747-400
that they were able to fly non-stop
directly between London and Sydney in
just a little over 20 hours. The first
time that anyone had managed to fly a
commercial airliner between them
directly without ever stopping. However,
that flight utilized special [music]
fuel and it didn't contain any
passengers or cargo on board to save on
weight and to extend range. [music]
Fully loaded, the 747 still couldn't
ever make the journey non-stop and as it
would turn out, Qantas' 1989 test flight
would be the first and last direct
flight made between London and Sydney
for the next three decades. For the most
part, for more than two decades since
2004, the longest non-stop commercial
flight in the world has been offered by
Singapore Airlines between Singapore and
the New York City area. At first,
between Singapore Changi Airport and
Newark and since 2020, between Singapore
Changi and New York JFK. The route
covers a distance of 15,344
km and takes roughly 18 and a half hours
to complete. The distance between Sydney
and London is much greater than this at
just over 17,000 km. And for the
entirety of the 21st century so far, no
direct route between them has yet come
into existence. Traditionally in modern
times, there have been four primary
flight routes to take [music] between
them. Qantas along with rivals like
Singapore Airlines and British Airways
have offered the fastest and most direct
route with a one-stop flight between
them and Singapore. [music]
Generally, upon arrival in Singapore,
passengers on the flight will deplane
while the plane is serviced, cleaned,
[music] and refueled before they reboard
and take back off again. They generally
spend around 2 hours down on the ground
in Singapore, in addition to the time it
takes to land and take back off again.
Well, the entire journey gate-to-gate
between Sydney and London generally
takes a bit more than 25 hours on
average to complete. Other routes
operated by Persian Gulf Airlines, like
Emirates, Etihad, and Qatar Airways,
offer similar one-stop service routing
through Dubai, Abu Dhabi, or Doha. But,
these are slightly longer than the route
through Singapore and are also prone to
wartime disruptions due to broader
Middle Eastern instability issues. There
are much longer, but sometimes cheaper
routes through Asian connection points
like Tokyo, Hong Kong, Istanbul, Delhi,
or Bangkok. And since 2018, there's been
Qantas's non-stop service between Perth
and London to consider as well. Because
Perth is about 1/6 closer to London than
Sydney, in the 1970s, Qantas was able to
introduce one-stop service between Perth
and London more than a decade before it
was able to offer the same service
between Sydney and London. And in the
2010s and '20s, Qantas has similarly
been able to offer non-stop service
between Perth and London first as well.
Lasting for around 18 [music] hours, the
non-stop Perth to London flight is
currently the third longest-lasting
non-stop flight in the world. Well, it
also offer travelers from Sydney the
ability to have another one-stop flight
option to London with a stopover point
in Perth along the way. It was also,
notably, the first-ever direct non-stop
[music] commercial flight established
between the European and Australian
continents, which itself was already a
huge accomplishment. But, there was
still no direct non-stop flight between
Sydney and London.
>> [music]
>> And in 2017, just before the non-stop
Perth to London service was started,
Qantas decided to begin setting the
pieces in a motion to finally change
that.
>> [music]
>> In August of 2017, Qantas unveiled
Project Sunrise, their ambition to
finally achieve a non-stop direct
commercial flight between Sydney and
London. The sunrise part of the name was
both a nod to Qantas's history of
pushing the boundaries of long-haul air
travel with the double sunrise flights
of the 1940s between Perth and Sri
Lanka, and to the fact that passengers
flying directly between Sydney and
London would also experience two
sunrises while on board. Qantas
challenged both Boeing and Airbus to
engineer an aircraft that could actually
handle flying the route with a full
payload of cargo and passengers on
board, and both companies quickly got to
work with their designs. Two years later
in 2019, both companies submitted their
designs to Qantas, but then in 2020, the
COVID-19 pandemic placed a sharp halt on
the planning for the project. For the
next 2 years, Project Sunrise was
effectively frozen and put on hold until
the summer of 2022, when Qantas
ultimately decided to go with the Airbus
proposal for a modified version of the
Airbus A350 that they called the
A350-1000
ULR, for ultra-long range. When compared
with a conventional A350-1000,
the A350-1000 ULR is designed to have an
extended range of 1,000 [music]
extra nautical miles. This was
accomplished by adding an additional
fuel tank on board that can carry an
extra 20,000
L of fuel, added structural
reinforcements to the airframe support
the added takeoff weight, and by
reducing the number of passengers on
board for more than 300 to only 238 to
save on payload weight. With these
modifications in place, the A350-1000
ULR will be capable of flying more than
17,000 km non-stop for at least 22
hours. Or in other words, just long
enough to be able to fly non-stop
between Sydney and London. Qantas placed
an order for 12 of these A350-1000 ULRs
from Airbus to service the London to
Sydney route,
>> [music]
>> with the expectation the service would
begin in late 2025. Unfortunately,
during the aircraft certification
process in 2024, regulatory concerns
arose around the design of the
aircraft's extra fuel tank, and Airbus
was compelled to completely redesign it,
which delayed the project again. The
first deliveries of the new aircraft
were then expected to be made at Qantas
in late 2026, but then in early 2026,
Qantas announced that due to unexpected
supply chain disruptions that were
affecting Airbus's production, the first
aircraft delivery wouldn't actually be
made until early 2027. So, currently,
the A350-1000 ULR certification and
testing flights are taking place in
Europe, while Qantas and Airbus
anticipate that the first deliveries of
the aircraft will be made during the
first half of 2027.
With Project Sunrise's non-stop service
between Sydney and London set to finally
commence in the second half of 2027, a
full decade after Qantas first announced
the start of the project in 2017.
And once it's in service, after finally
eliminating the final stop along the
Kangaroo route in Singapore that's been
around since the 1980s, it will reduce
the total travel time between London and
Sydney to just 22 hours, shedding
between three and four hours from the
fastest journey that's available today.
And for the first time in history,
[music]
offering commercial air travel between
the two cities are nearly opposite ends
of the earth in less than a single day.
And it will also blow the Singapore to
New York flight out of the water for the
longest non-stop flight in the world,
beating that route's record that has
been held for more than two decades
since 2004.
Now, sitting on a flight for 22 straight
hours might sound like a nightmare to a
lot of people still, but it's much
better than the travel options of the
past were. While Qantas is also doing
everything that it can to make the
flight as unpainful as possible. The 238
seats on board will be divided into six
very spacious first-class suites up
front that resemble a studio apartment,
followed by 52 business class suites
that'll feature closable doors for
privacy, 40 premium economy seats, and
then 140 economy seats that'll offer a
generous 33-in seat pitch. More than
most economy seats anywhere else do.
Qantas is also adding what it calls a
well-being zone on board the flights as
well, which will give passengers a
dedicated space to stand, stretch,
exercise, and move around while on board
for 22 continuous hours. In addition to
the route to London, [music] Qantas is
also planning on using the A350-1000 ULR
to launch a direct non-stop route
between Sydney and New York City for the
first time as well, which will be great
for travelers between these cities
who've traditionally had to layover
somewhere in between like Dallas or Los
Angeles first. But coming in at about
1,000 km closer to Sydney than London
is, the New York City flights will be a
bit shorter and faster. In the future,
Qantas might use the extended range of
the A350-1000 ULR to open up more direct
routes to London and New York from other
major Australian cities like Melbourne
and Brisbane. But either way, once
Project Sunrise begins with their
non-stop flights between Sydney and
London in 2027, one of the holy grails
of commercial aviation will have finally
been reached. Since the very first
flight was made between London and
Sydney all the way back in 1919, that
took nearly 28 entire days to
accomplish, it's only taken a little
more than a century of continuous
innovation and progress to get that
total travel time down to less than 1
day. And I think that that is nothing
less than one of the most incredible
achievements of the modern era. And it's
something I believe that all of humanity
should collectively take pride in.
Meanwhile, in the United States, one of
the most concerning things about living
here, besides not yet having direct New
York City to Sydney flights, is that
there are pretty weak data privacy laws
and a ton of personal data that gets put
out into the public record, frequently
by local, state, and federal governments
themselves. It's always been like that
here, and it wasn't really ever a huge
problem before the advent of the
internet. But these days, it means that
people are able to turn a profit off of
making it easier for other people to get
your personal information, and they do.
They're called people sites, and if you
want to see for yourself, just search
your name and address or phone number,
and you'll probably come across a bunch
of these sites that list at least some
of your personal information.
>> [music]
>> But you also have the power to change
this. You have the legal right to
request that your personal data is
removed from each and every one of these
sites. The biggest problem is that it
takes forever to actually do that. They
make it as hard as possible, and you
have to do it individually over and over
again for every single one of the
endless sites that have it. But that's a
problem that this video's sponsor,
Incogni, fixes. [music] They'll do this
entire process for you on your behalf.
They constantly search through the
internet for any of your personal data
that's out there, and they'll go through
the whole process of taking it all down,
including handling any and all
rejections. Letting Incogni handle all
of this is not only great for your peace
of mind, but it can also really help cut
down on obnoxious spam calls and emails,
since it's these very same services that
sell your data in bulk. I've been an
actual customer of Incogni for years
now, so I know that it really works, and
I found the cost to be very well worth
it. And it'll be even more worth it for
you, because Incogni is offering you 60%
off of their annual plan when you click
the button here on your screen right now
or when you go to
incogni.com/reallifelore
or by following the link that's down
below in the description and use code
reallifelore.
It's a great way to help support my
channel and the journalism that I'm
trying to do here as well. And as
always, thank you so much for watching.